Dorothea Dix Lawrence Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Dorothea Dix Lawrence Collection 1856-1980 (bulk 1902-1980)
ML31.L39
Lawrence, Dorothea Dix, 1899-1979
230 items 4 containers 2 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Dorothea Dix Lawrence was a successful opera singer in the 1930s and 1940s who later became a recitalist and folklorist. The materials in the collection include correspondence, photographs, clippings and other items that document her career as a singer and interpreter of American folk music. In addition, the collection includes her articles on American folklore that were published in various journals and two copies of her famous Folklore Music Map of the United States. The collection also includes piano-vocal opera scores and a large number of American folk songs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Lawrence, Dorothea Dix, 1899-1979--Autographs.; Lawrence, Dorothea Dix, 1899-1979--Correspondence.; Lawrence, Dorothea Dix, 1899-1979--Photographs.; Lawrence, Dorothea Dix, 1899-1979.; Lawrence, Dorothea Dix, 1899-1979.
Subjects
Folk music--United States--History and criticism.; Folk songs, English--United States.; Operas--Vocal scores with piano.; Songs, English--United States.; Sopranos (Singers)--United States--Correspondence.
Form/Genre
Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Photographic prints.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Morgan Lawrence, the son of Dorothea Dix Lawrence; 1980.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
A taped interview with Morgan Lawrence, the son of Dorothea Dix Lawrence, was conducted on July 1, 1980, by Jon Newson, assistant chief of the Library of Congress Music Division. The tape had been sealed until July 1, 2005. It was transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division and is now accessible to the public.
Access and Restrictions
The Dorothea Dix Lawrence Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Sketch
Date Event
1899 September 22 Born in New York City
1929 Made opera debuts: Montreal, Quebec City, Canada
1932 Appeared as Aida with Philadelphia Opera Company, San Carlo Opera Company Made concert debuts: Studebaker Theatre, Chicago; Jordan Hall, Boston Produced, directed and performed in weekly radio show Twilight Hour, Trenton, New Jersey
1939 Appeared in the opening concert of the New York World's Fair Created Primer of American Music for WPEN Philadelphia (27 weekly broadcasts) sponsored by the Board of Education, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
1946 Published Folklore Music Map of the United States Produced, directed and starred in Folklore Musicana, an 8-week series on radio station WNYC, New York City
1949 Collaborated with Gloria Swanson in the television production Design for Living on WPIX-TV, New York City
1959 Published Folklore Songs of the United States (collaboration with Walter Rosemont)
1970 Retired from public life
1979 May 23 Died in Plainfield, New Jersey
Scope and Content Note
The Dorothea Dix Lawrence Collection consists of the correspondence, photographs, clippings, and writings of this noted operatic singer, recitalist, lecturer, and folklorist. The collection also includes piano-vocal opera scores and a large number of American folk songs.
Organization of the Dorothea Dix Lawrence Collection
The Dorothea Dix Lawrence Collection is organized into two series:
Biographical Materials
Music
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006569269
Container List
- Biographical Materials (Boxes 1, 3)
  Contains biographical summaries, correspondence, writings, a radio script, clippings, photographs, an award certificate, and Folklore Music Map of the United States (oversize concert poster).
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material, and chronologically therein.
  - Biographical summaries (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Writings: Folklore Society of Great Britain (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Writings: Thirtieth International Congress of Americanists, August 1952 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Writings: Periodicals (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Writings: Folklore Music Map of the United States; photocopied collages of clippings and concert programs (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Radio (script) (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Clippings 1937-1980 see also Biographical Materials (Series). Writings: Folklore Music Map of the U. S. [Box-Folder 3/1] (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Concert programs/advertisements see also Biographical Materials (Series). Writings: Folklore Music Map of the U. S. [Box-Folder 3/1] (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Photographs: Portraits (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Photographs: Miss Lawrence with others (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Photographs: miscellaneous (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Photographs: oversize (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Award: New York City - - USO - - Joint War Appeal. Certificate of Achievement (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Folklore Music Map of the United States; oversize concert poster (housed in Map Case, drawer 3) (Box-folder 3/3)
- Music (Boxes 2-4)
  Contains piano-vocal opera scores and other operatic vocal collections, various art songs and American folk songs.
  Arranged by type of music, and alphabetically by composer therein.
  - Opera (Box 2-3)
    - Gounod, Charles Faust; New York: G. Schirmer, 1902, Printed piano-vocal score; 323 p.; Leather-bound, name embossed on cover.; Annotated. (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Puccini, Giacomo Tosca; New York: Boosey and Co., 1905, Printed piano-vocal score; 335 p.; Leather-bound, name embossed on cover.; Annotated. (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Strauss, Richard Salome; London: Boosey & Hawkes, 1943, Printed piano-vocal score; 203 p.; Annotated. (Box-folder 3/4)
    - [Various] Opera songs. The Choicest selection from all of the standard operas new and old. (Old book 1: soprano); Philadelphia: Theodore Presser Co., 1930, Printed piano-vocal score; 234 p.; Leather-bound, name embossed on cover.; Annotated. (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Verdi, Giuseppe La Traviata; New York: G. Schirmer, 1926, Printed piano-vocal score; 232 p.; Leather-bound, name embossed on cover.; Annotated. (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Songs (Box 2-4)
    - Anonymous (Box-folder 4/16)
      - The Barren pines. Scene II, Ozalid piano-vocal score; pp. 26-28; bound.; [Used on radio broadcast (?)].
      - Bucking broncho; Cowboy Jack, Ms. piano-vocal score; 4 p.; Little America (broadcast) Oct. 12, 1940.
    - Cadman, Charles Wakefield (Box-folder 4/1)
      - The Moon drops low. New York: Edwin H. Morris, 1909, Printed piano-vocal score; 7 p.; Text by Nelle Richmond Eberhart.
      - Spring song of the robin woman. New York: White-Smith Music, 1918, Printed piano-vocal score; 9 p.; Text by Nelle Richmond Eberhart.
      - Her shadow (Ojibway canoe song). New York: White-Smith Music, 1918, Printed piano-vocal score; 5 p.; Words and music by Frederick R. Burton (rearranged and harmonized by C. Cadman).
    - Combs, Josia [ed.] (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Schirmer's American folk-song series, Set I: Folk-songs from the Kentucky highlands. New York: G. Schirmer, 1939, Printed piano-vocal score; 40 p.
    - Endicott, Samuel [arr.] (Box-folder 4/16)
      - He stole my tender heart away. New York: G. Schirmer, 1939, Printed piano-vocal score; 40 p.
    - Farwell, Arthur (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Bird song dance., Ms. piano-vocal score; [2 p.]
      - Inketunga's Thunder Song., Ms. piano-vocal score; 3 p.; [Singing exercises written on back page].
      - The Sabbath, op. 105, no. 3., Ozalid piano-vocal score; 3 p.; Text by Emily Dickinson.
      - Song of the Deathless Voice., Ms. piano-vocal score; 4 p.
    - Foster, Stephen (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Come where my love lies dreaming. Boston: Oliver Ditson Company, 1906, Printed piano-vocal score; 7 p.
    - Gardner, A. T. (Box-folder 4/16)
      - I know two eyes, two soft brown eyes., Ms. piano-vocal score; 2 p.
    - Hare, Maude Cuney [arr.] (Box-folder 4/4)
      - Six Creole folk songs. New York: Carl Fisher, 1921, Printed piano-vocal score; 24 p.
    - Haubiel, Charles [arr.] (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Mother Goose songs. First series. New York: The Composers Press, 1939, Printed piano-vocal score; 24 p.
    - Haubiel, Charles [arr.] (Box-folder 4/17)
      - The Dog and the tramps., Ozalid piano-vocal score; 1 p. [incomplete].
      - Little Bo Peep., Ms. piano-vocal score; 3 p.
      - Little Boy Blue., Ms. piano-vocal score; 4 p.
      - Little Jack Horner., Ms. piano-vocal score; 4 p.
      - Mistress Mary., Ms. piano-vocal score; 3 p.
    - Hopkinson, Francis (Box-folder 4/5)
      - Colonial love lyrics: Six songs by Francis Hopkinson. Boston: A.P. Schmidt, 1919, Printed piano-vocal score; 29 p.; Edited and augmented by Harold V. Milligan.
      - O'er the hills., Ms. piano-vocal score; 6 p.; Edited and augmented by Harold V. Milligan.
      - My dreams have been so wondrous free., Ms. piano-vocal score; 3 p.; Edited and augmented by Harold V. Milligan.
      - [Songs by Francis Hopkinson: Come fair Rosina, etc.]., Ozalid copies of early printing; 11 leaves [wire brad binding removed]
    - Hopkinson, Francis (Box-folder 4/7)
      - [Songs by Francis Hopkinson: The Garland, etc.]., Ozalid copies of early printing; 5 leaves [wire brad binding removed]
    - Huarte, Julian (Box-folder 4/16)
      - Madrigal Español. New York: G. Schirmer, 1992, Printed piano-vocal score, 6 p. [incomplete]
    - Lawrence, Dorothea Dix [compiler] (Box-folder 3/5-6)
      - Folklore-songs of the United States. New York: The Dorothea Dix Lawrence Folklore Society, U.S.A., 1959, Printed piano-vocal score; 133 p.; Arrangements by Walter Rosemont.
    - MacDowell, Edward (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Six selected songs. Boston: A.P. Schmidt, 1940, Printed piano-vocal score, 18 p. [incomplete]
    - Nelson, Nils A. (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Passing. New York: February 1933, Ozalid copy; 2 p.; Inscribed to Miss Lawrence by the composer.
    - Niles, John Jacob [ed.] (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Schirmer's American folk-song series, Set 14: Songs of the hill-folk (twelve ballads from Kentucky, Virginia, and North Carolina). New York: G. Schirmer, 1934, Printed piano-vocal score; 25 p.
      - Schirmer's American folk-song series, Set 16: Ten Christmas carols (from the Southern Appalachian Mountains). New York: G. Schirmer, 1935, Printed piano-vocal score; 22 p.
      - Schirmer's American folk-song series, Set 18: Ballads, carols, and tragic legends (from the Southern Appalachian Mountains). New York: G. Schirmer, 1937, Printed piano-vocal score; 22 p.
    - Rodrigo, Joaquin (Box-folder 4/10)
      - Villancicos. Madrid: Edición del autor, 1953, Printed piano-vocal score; 7 p.; Inscribed: "Para Miss Dorothea Dix Lawrence con toda simpatia" [signature illegible, but likely that of the composer].
    - Rosemont, Walter L. (Box-folder 4/11)
      - Ye Olde historic inn., Ms. piano-vocal score; 3 leaves; On title page: "Written especially for Miss Dorothea Dix Lawrence for her broadcasts."
      - The Railroad cars are coming., Ms. piano-vocal score; 2 p.; Adapted and arranged by Walter L. Rosemont.
      - El Zapatero (The Shoemaker)., Ms. piano-vocal score; 1 leaf; Adapted and arranged by Walter L. Rosemont.
      - Invocation to the Sun God: Zuñi Indian mother's prayer, 1950., Ozalid copy; 2 p.; Adapted and arranged by Walter L. Rosemont.
    - Sullivan, Marian Dix (Box-folder 4/12)
      - For Lo! The Winter is past. Boston, 1856., Ms. piano-vocal score; 1 p.
      - The Star-Spangled Banner., Ms. piano-vocal score; 2 p.; Harmonized and arranged by Thomas Grasso for Dorothea D. Lawrence.; [Both pieces in same binder].
    - Troyer, Carlos [arr.] (Box-folder 4/13)
      - Traditional songs of the Zuñi Indians. Philadelphia: Theo. Presser Co., 1904, Printed piano-vocal scores; Contents:; The Sunrise Call, or Echo song.; Incantation upon a sleeping infant.; Invocation to the Sun God.; Zuñi lover's wooing.; Sunset song.; Hunting song of the Cliff Dwellers.; Two Zuñian melodies.
    - (Box-folder 4/14)
      - Villancicos. New York: G. Ricordi & Co., Inc., 1922, Printed piano-vocal score; 7 p.; Text by William Alexander Percy.
    - (Box-folder 4/15)
      - The Lonesome dove., Ms. piano-vocal score; 4 p.; Text by Arnold Sundgaard.